A Guide to the Autograph Collection, 1793-1945
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Autograph Collection, 1793-1945
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9030-a
This collection contains 19 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased by the Library in 1968.
Alternative Form
Also available as photocopies.
Scope and Content Information
Includes a letter, 1793, from Richard Henry Lee to Richard Clough Anderson, concerning lands Anderson is surveying for Revolutionary War claims, especially those involving Lee's children who have inherited some claims.
Also includes a letter, 1836, from James Barbour to David Allen concerning his blooded horses and stock improvement; and a letter, 1883, from Fitzhugh Lee to Henry Cleveland concerning a letter of Robert E. Lee sent to Cleveland for facsimile reproduction.
Also includes letters, n.d., from Richard Harding Davis to Charles Belmont Davis concerning a visit to Lady Astor and her family at their country house and social news; and to Seymour Hicks concerning a visit to England, a possible writing project, family matters, and the perfidy of the Germans.
Also includes a letter, n.d., from Ellen Glasgow, New York, to Blanche Wolf Knopf offering condolences to Knopf for her mother's illness.
Contents List
- James Barbour, Barboursville, to David Allen near Pratte Town 5 Oct 1836
  James Barbour (1775-1842) was elected Speaker of the House of Delegates of Virginia in 1809 and remained in this post until his election as Governor of Virginia in 1812. In 1815, Barbour was elected to the United States Senate, and he served as a senator until 1825 when he was appointed to the cabinet. He remained on the cabinet until 1828 when he requested the position of minister to Great Britain. He remained in Britain until 1829. When he returned to the United States, he attempted to get back into Virginia politics, but was not very successful. He was not very active in politics hereafter, and he spent most of his time at his home in Barboursville.
  This letter to David Allen was written during his later years. In it he discusses some of the horses that he owns and would like for Allen to see. Some of these horses are imported, and of fine stock. Barbour hopes to interest Allen in purchasing one of his studs as Allen owns a large stock of mares. He offers to send one of the studs to Allen to "try him for a season at the end thereof if you like buy him, if not return him with such a portion of the profits... as may be equitable.. ."
- Henry Clay, Washington, to John W. Hunt, Lexington, KY 22 Jan 1818, Photocopy
  Henry Clay (1777-1852) was a congressman, senator, and secretary of state during his long political career. He was born in Virginia, but spent most of his life and career in Kentucky. When this letter was written, he was a congressman.
  He begins the letter by mentioning a "Report of our Bank Committee" and "the Report of the Condition of the Banks of Pennsylvania to the Legislature of that state, which you will find curious." He also asks for advice and assistance in selling some of his property in Kentucky, either in town or near his home, Ashland, "... say 200 acres, lying on the Tate's Creek road to be laid off parallel with the Boone's road.. ." He also mentions the discussion of [Andrew] Jackson's conduct of the Seminole War (in Congress), which he will bitterly denouce in 1819.
- Richard Harding Davis, Mount Kisco, NY to Seymour Hicks 6 Apr (ante 1912)
  Richard Harding Davis (1864-1916), the son of Rebecca Harding Davis, was both a prominent journalist and author. He began his career as a journalist in 1886 with the Philadelphia Record and soon moved on to the Press and the Telegraph, which sent him to England. In 1889, he worked for the New York Sun, and he also wrote for Scribner's Magazine. In 1890, he became the managing editor for Harper's Weekly. He gained prominence as a journalist, in part, because of his reporting on six prominent wars: the Spanish War in Cuba; the Graeco-Turkish War; the Spanish- American War; the Boer War, the Russo-Japanese War, and World War I. He wrote numerous short stories and a few novels.
  This letter was written after 1912, because he mentions his wife "Bessie" (Elizabeth G. McEvoy) whom he married in 1912. In this letter, he reminisces about his time in England with Seymour and Ella. He also mentions that "... Bessie worries over the Zepps." He describes them as "murderers and cowards, and to no end, except their own damnation. We should never be satisfied until Germany is so completed (sic) wiped out that she is remembered only as a stench, like a stinking caudle."
- Richard Harding Davis, Crossroads Farm, Mount Kisco, NY to Seymour Hicks 6 Apr
  In this letter Davis inquires "how long before the production you will begin to want the new book, as I am coming across to go over it with you." He mentions that in "Central America there is lots of chance for local color.. ."
- Richard Harding Davis, Cliveden Taplow to his brother 24 Dec
  In this letter Davis describes his visit to a large family home in the countryside of England, and his activities there.
- Ralph Waldo Emerson, Concord, to William Cullen Bryant, New York 11 Apr 1840
  In this letter from Ralph Waldo Emerson (1803-1882), he is writing a letter of introduction to William Cullen Bryant for a Mr. Alexander Hume. Emerson was residing in Concord with his second wife at this time. Emerson wrote a letter for Hume to take with him when he visits Bryant. William Cullen Bryant (1794-1878) is the editor of the Evening Post at the time of this letter.
- Ralph Waldo Emerson, Manchester, to J. W. Hudson 5 Nov 1847
  In this letter, Emerson mentions being in Liverpool, and that he is awaiting further details on a ".. .series of engagments you now offer me with Mr. Ireland.. ." and how these should be arranged.
- Ellen Glasgow, New York, to Mrs. Knopf Saturday
  This letter from Ellen Glasgow (1873-1945) to Mrs. Knopf is a letter of sympathy over Mrs. Knopf's mother's illness.
- Benjamin Harrison, Richmond, to Mr. Short, with an additional note in Harrison's hand 30 Sept 1785 & 20 Oct, Copy
  Benjamin Harrison (1726?-1791) was a member of the Virginia House of Burgesses, a Revolutionary statesman, a signer of the Declaration of Independence, a member of the Virginia House of Delegates, and Govenor of Virginia. This letter was written during his last years in the House of Delegates.
  Harrison has written a note dated 20 Oct. at the end of a (secretary's) copy of a 30 Sept. 1785 letter to "Short". In this letter, Harrison refers to money hge is sending to Short. He mentions Col. Henry Lee, Short's brother Peyton, Mr. Morris, someone named Nelson, and Tazewell. He also mentions the death of Mr. Dandridge who was on the Bench. He also states that "... my own friends have withheld from me sums of m[oney] to such an amount that they have thrown me into the most embarrassing situation and it will puzzle me to get out of it.. ." In his note of 20 Oct., Harrison writes "Above is a copy of what I wrote you by the [las]t french packett.. ."
- Bret Harte, 713 B'way to W.W. Astor 5 Jan 1878
  In this letter to Astor, Harte asks him to recall a conversation in which he and Astor discussed the possibility of Astor finding him a "position". Because Harte has been ill, he has not been able to write very much recently, and therefore, he really needs a job.
- Fitzhugh Lee, Richland, Stafford Co., Va. to Mr. Henry W. Cleveland 16 Jan 1883
  Fitzhugh Lee (1835-1905) was the nephew of Gen. Robert E. Lee, a lieutenant-colonel in the C.S.A., and governor of Virginia from 1885-1889.
  This letter discusses who his famous uncle was named for, and mentions that he is sending Cleveland one of Gen. Lee's letters "... about a dog I procured for him." And he tells Cleveland that "You are at liberty to use any part of it for fac-simile provided you will return the letter."
- Richard Henry Lee to Col. Richard Anderson, Surveyor of Military rights for the Virginia Continental Line in Jefferson Co., Kentucky 4 Dec 1793 (Oversize P-17)
  Richard Henry Lee (1732-1794) was a Revolutionary statesman, a member of the House of Burgesses, a signer of the Declaration of Independence, and a senator for Virginia until 1792. This letter was written in the last year of his life after he returned to his home "Chantilly" in Westmoreland Co.
  This letter concerns two survey reports that Anderson conducted for him. The surveys never made it to the Richmond Land Office, which makes it impossible for Lee or his son, Cassius, to reap the benefits of the military rights to this land which they hold.
- Amy Lowell, Heath Street, Brookline, Mass. to Mrs. Clark 11 Dec 1916
  Amy Lowell (1874-1925) was born in Brookline, Mass. in the same house in which she died. She did not become a serious poet until around 1902. After this time, she devoted most of her time to poetry.
  This letter concerns the arrangements for one of her readings. The reading is scheduled for March 27, and Lowell suggests that the title be "Modern Trends in Poetry" or a reading of her own verse. She describes herself as an invalid, and would rather stay at a hotel because she would rest better there. Lowell writes that she will accept the $50 for her expenses that the Committee has offered her.
- John Mosby, San Francisco to Harry E. Peck 19 April 1887
  John Singleton Mosby (1833-1916) lived near Charlottesville during his childhood. He entered the University of Virginia in 1849. Later on he was admitted to the bar in Bristol, Va., and he practised law until the beginning of the Civil War in 1861, at which time he enlisted in the cavalry. Mosby participated in the Bull Run campaign, and he was a Confederate Ranger. After the war, he practised law in Virginia. In 1878 he was appointed consul at Hong Kong, where he remained until 1885. In 1887, he published Mosby's War Reminiscences and Stuarty's Cavalry Campaigns. This letter was probably written while he was a land agent in Colorado.
  This letter was probably written while he was a land agent in Colorado. In it, Mosby is responding to an inquiry about his injuries in a battle near Fairfax Court House, Virginia on August 17, 1863. Mosby replies that he did not remember the exact date, but he was shot twice and severely wounded. "My own surgeon did not consider the would mortal but it was so reported at the time." He mentions other wounds suffered in later battles, and that his son in Denver has the memoir of his command should Peck want further details.
- Edm. Pendleton to John Skinker, King George Co. 16 Feb. 1785
  Edmund Pendleton (1721-1803) was a Virginia jurist and Revolutionary War patriot. Early in his career, he practised law and later on became a justice of the peace of Caroline Co., Va. He was elected to the House of Burgesses and became treasurer of the colony. He was very active in the formation of the new state following the Revolutionary War.
  This letter concerns a debt owed Col. Brooke by Col. Carter and some misunderstanding between them regarding this debt.
- Roger A. Pryor, Richmond to T. P. Kettell, esq. 9 March 1857
  Roger Atkinson Pryor (1828-1919) was a descendant of the Blands and Randolphs of Virginia and of Lucy Eppes Atkinson. He studied law at UVA (1846-47) and practised law briefly in Charlottesville and Petersburg. He founded and edited the Southside Democrat in Petersburg and was associated with the Washington Union, and the Richmond Enquirer. In 1857, he also founded The South, which was published in Washington, and he was associated with the Washington States. He was elected to Congress, and he served in this position until he was resigned to join the Confederacy in 1861. After the war, he moved to New York to continue his careers in journalism and law.
  This letter concerns a weekly editorial for the Washington Union that he is hoping T.P. Kettell will write. Pryor writes, "I would like you to pay special attention to the great southern staples, cotton & tobacco, & to public improvements, (etc.). I will advise you in time for the first issue of my paper. It may be as well to inform you that I mean to announce that my letter are from your pen."
- Poem "Courage" by Celia Thaxter n.d.
  Celia Laighton Thaxter (1835-1894) spent her you among some of the most prominent poets and writers of her time, such as Lowell, Thoreau and Whittier. Lowell had one of her poems published without her knowledge, giving her a start in publishing. She began to have more of her poetry published. She married Levi Lincoln Thaxter, her childhood tutor, and they had three sons.
- Bushrod Washington 29 July 1794
  Bushrod Washington (1762-1829) was an associate justice of the United States Supreme Court. The nephew of Pres. George Washington, he was born in Westmoreland Co., Va. Bushrod was a soldier in the Continental Army, and after the Revolutionary War, he studied law in Philadelphia. He began his legal practice in Alexandria, Va., and was elected to the Va. House of Delegates in 1787, and a year later to the Va. State Convention. In 1798, he was appointed to the Supreme Court. During his tenure, the Supreme Court began to gain prominence.
  This 1794 document was written during his time spent in Richmond, Va., and it deals with a dispute over land between the Swearingens and a Mr. Browning, and it sets forth Washington's opinion on the situation.
- George Washington, Philadelphia to Joseph Barrell 30 March 1794, Photocopy
  This was a letter to Mr. Barrell thanking him for his gift of a sea otter skin, which was presented by Col. Sargent.